<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tocsin, or watch-bell sent to the king, queene regent, princes of blood, to all the parlaments, magistrates, officers, and loyall subiects of France. Against the booke of the popes temporall power, not long since set forth by Cardinall Bellarmine Iesuite. By Memnons Statue. With the permission of the best genie of Fraunce. And done into English by I.R. ...</title>
            <title>Tocsin au roy. English</title>
            <author>Le Jay, Nicolas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113759</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848989</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848989</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14117</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14117)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1057:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tocsin, or watch-bell sent to the king, queene regent, princes of blood, to all the parlaments, magistrates, officers, and loyall subiects of France. Against the booke of the popes temporall power, not long since set forth by Cardinall Bellarmine Iesuite. By Memnons Statue. With the permission of the best genie of Fraunce. And done into English by I.R. ...</title>
                  <title>Tocsin au roy. English</title>
                  <author>Le Jay, Nicolas.</author>
                  <author>I. R., fl. 1611.</author>
                  <author>France. Parliament (Paris)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Stansby] for Edward White the younger, and are to be sold at the little North doore of Paules, at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Memnons Statue = Nicolas Le Jay.</note>
                  <note>A translation, by I.R., of: Le Jay, Nicolas. Le tocsin au roy, which is a response to the "Tractatus de potestate summi pontificis in temporalibus, adversus Guilielmu Barclaium" of Roberto Bellarmino.</note>
                  <note>Includes "An extract of the registers of the Court of the Parliament of Paris" which has a separate dated title page (register is continuous).</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴ (H4 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bellarmino, Roberto Francesco Romolo, --  Saint, 1542-1621. --  Tractatus de potestate summi pontificis in temporalibus, adversus Guilielmu Barclaium.</term>
               <term>Popes --  Temporal power --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE TOCSIN, <hi>OR,</hi> WATCH-BELL: <hi>Sent</hi> TO THE KING, QVEENE Regent, Princes of blood, to all the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laments, Magiſtrates, Officers, and loyall Subiects of FRANCE.</p>
                  <p>Againſt the booke of the Popes temporall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, not long ſince ſet forth by Cardinall BELLARMINE Ieſuite.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By</hi> MEMNONS <hi>Statue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>With the permiſsion of the beſt Genie of Fraunce. And done into Engliſh by <hi>I. R.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Notate: Verbae</l>
                     <l>Signate: Myſteriae</l>
                     <l>Ecce enim myſterium vobis dico.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Edward White</hi> the younger, and are to be ſold at the little North doore of Paules, at the ſigne of the Gunne. 1611.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:2"/>
                  <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE LOYALL Hearted Subiects of ENGLAND.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Author of this ſmall Treatiſe teſtifieth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be a true hearted ſubiect to the Crowne of France, by compoſing it; J will likewiſe (in emulation and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his fidelity) approue my ſelfe to be no leſſe to the Crowne of England, by tranſlating it. For ſith this bloudy booke of Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (ambitiouſly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating to himſelfe the Title of the
<pb facs="tcp:14117:3"/>Popes <hi>Temporall power</hi>) though par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly ſent to France, is neuertheleſſe meant, and doth concerne all other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Soueraignties and free States whatſoeuer; I thought in honour to God, in alleageance to my Prince, in loue to my Countrie, and in duetie to all, J was bound to diſpoile out of his French habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements, and to ſute in our Engliſh attire this iudicious and compendious Treatiſe, which ſo worthily oppoſeth and impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it. Come, nay then run, if not flie hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you loyall hearted Engliſh men, and as the choiſe of the wiſest, chiefeſt and loyalleſt hearted French haue already, ſo in religion, in zeale, in diſcretion and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice doe you now commit and ſacrifice to the fire both <hi>Bellarmines</hi> booke, and the thought, much more the practiſe of thoſe irreligious, vſurping and ſanguynat ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and poſitions therein contained, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:14117:3"/>to the diſgrace, preiudice, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction both of our Kings &amp; Countries; yea for euer (in your hearts and ſoules) not onely ſpit at, but defie the wrongfull, tyrannicall, Jeſuiticall and Diabolicall pretence of this (Sophiſticall traytor, and treacherous Sophiſter) <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who (as ſubtlely as inueterately) aimeth, not to reach at, but to take off the Crownes of Kings, and (iniuſtlie) to place them vpon the heads of Popes; yea to trample their Scepters and Regall Ornaments vnder their feet, and to bring their Dominions and ſubiects, both into a wofull deſolation and a miſerable ſubiection and ſlauerie.</p>
                  <p>For alas, ſhall we permit to ſee, or liue to permit that our Roiall Kings of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (not inferior to anie, but equall with the greateſt Kings of the world) ſhould now (through our negligence) be made homagers, ſubiects, nay ſlaues vnto Popes
<pb facs="tcp:14117:4"/>(Gods mortall enemies, and our deadly profeſſed foes) as was our King <hi>Iohn,</hi> the Emperour <hi>Fredericke Barbaroſſa,</hi> the King of Nauarre, and Earle of Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe, &amp;c.)</p>
                  <p>No, no, illustrious and generous Nobilitie, iudicious and faithfull priuie Counſellors, learned and vpright Judges, reuerend and religious Prelates, valo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and warlike Gentry, incorruptible and watchfull Magiſtrates, faithful and vigilant Officers, obedient and loyall Commons; ioine all in one, yea, let euery mothers ſonne (if occaſion require) with an vnanime conſent, <hi>Viua Voce,</hi> cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and couragiouſly, with Drummes beating, Trumpets ſounding, and Canons roaring, denounce Warre to that Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, nay to that Pope, nay to that diuell, which preſumeth or durſt preſume to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue either our King of his ſoueraigntie,
<pb facs="tcp:14117:4"/>or our Countrey of her independencie: yea next and immediatly to the zeale of the glory of God, let vs be zealous &amp; watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, watchful and couragious, couragious and reſolute, for the ſecuritie and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of King <hi>IAMES</hi> our dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and his heires for euer; and for the conſeruation and maintaining of the Soueraigntie, both of his Crowne and Kingdome of England, the Paradice of the world, and our ſweet natiue Countrie.</p>
                  <p>And the more to incite, and powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incourage you in the performance of this your religious and ſworne duety; I haue tranſlated, publiſhed, and here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you this <hi>Tocſin,</hi> (or <hi>Watch-bell</hi>) that when you chaunce to ſleepe in your beddes of ſecuritie, it may arouſe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake you to ſtand vpon your guard, with Swordes drawne, Muskets charged, Match lighted, and hearts eagerlie ſharpened and animated to deſtroy and
<pb facs="tcp:14117:5"/>confound the Pope and his adhaerents, and to ſubuert and ouerthrow all other hoſtile enemies whatſoeuer, which ſhal ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incroach vpon our Temporalitie, or attempt to depriue vs of our Soueraignty; to the end that neither the fame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne of our deceaſed triumphant and victorious warriours (which hath hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpread it ſelfe to the fartheſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt parts of the world, and is for euer characteris'd vpon the neuer-dying Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of immortality) may not deſeruedly taunt &amp; taxe vs with the ſcandalous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of cowardiſe, nor our poſteritie hereafter, reuile and curſe vs for lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them inheritors and heires, onely to Tyrannicall ſlauery, and Presbyteriall ſeruitude: from the which God of his mercy preſerue &amp; defend both our ſelues and them. And hereunto let all the loyall hearted ſubiects of King <hi>Iames</hi> clappe hands, and ſay <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>By I. R.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:5"/>
                  <head>THE TOCSIN OR, WATCH-BELL.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rance, it is high time (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay) that this <hi>Tocſin</hi> (or <hi>Watch-bell</hi>) ſound ſhrilly in the hearts of all thy people, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake and giue the <hi>Alarum</hi> to all thoſe which ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee; ſith <hi>Cardinall Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine the Ieſuite</hi> (as impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently as vniuſtly) hath choſen the right of thy <hi>Kings</hi> minority, to giue the aſſault to thy <hi>Soueraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and to fixe the <hi>Petard</hi> to the gates of thy Maieſty, hitherto inuiolated.</p>
                  <p>He hath watched the time that thy <hi>Hercules Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the great,</hi> was tranſlated to a better Kingdome then thine, to leaue the Supreintendency thereof ill aſſured to the young King his heire, the Regency vncertaine to the Queene Regent, the ſucceſsion doubtfull to the <hi>Princes</hi> of blood, the authority de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit
<pb facs="tcp:14117:6"/>and feeble to the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> the care voy de of honour to the Magiſtrates, the loyalty without aſſurance to the Officers, the obedience without fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to the Subiects, and the peace without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance to our neighbours. For this booke publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of late in Rome, vnder the title of <hi>The Popes Temporall power,</hi> hath performed all, yea farre worſe then all this.</p>
                  <p>This proud Cardinall in his booke, depainteth vs Popes, as if each were a <hi>Cyrus,</hi> that is to ſay, inflamed with a deſire, both to haue and to commaund all: but our <hi>Queene Mary</hi> ſhall be to them a <hi>Tomiris,</hi> which authoriſed and incouraged in the right of her ſonne, ſhall not onely cut off the complots of thoſe Vſurpers, but alſo the intruſion of all others whatſoeuer. An acte both iuſt and neceſſary, ſith it is not done in contempt of the Apoſtolicke autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but contrariwiſe, to exempt vs from that bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage whereunto this <hi>Cardinall</hi> through his booke would bring vs: yea, and which he would cauſe to ſteale in to the buddes of the Flower-deluces, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to yoke and curbe the free necks of the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> which more iuſtly then all other <hi>Kings</hi> of the world may ſay,
<q>Filij Abrahae ſumus &amp; nemini ſeruiuimus vnquam.</q>
A iudicious perſonage of this Kingdome, as ſoone as he ſaw the diabolicall parricide committed and perpetrated vpon the ſacred perſon of our late King <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> and the Queene mother de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared <hi>Regent,</hi> he ſaid, that ſhee would be vnto our
<pb facs="tcp:14117:6"/>yong King, as the branch of the Plane tree, or as the Storke is to yer young ones, from whom ſhee kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth off all infection and venome.</p>
                  <p>And now it is that France expecteth of the ſaid Queene Regent, the fruits of the aforeſaid predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For if euer deadly poyſon ſpread it ſelfe ouer the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> it is now through this <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals Booke,</hi> which endeuoureth that the Maieſty and ſoueraignty of the Flower-deluces, ſhould tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally be made ſubiect vnto Popes. But alas, great Queene, what pittie, nay what griefe would it be to you, (you being the Tutrixe both of King and Kingdome) negligently to permit all France to be impoyſoned through one onely booke?</p>
                  <q>Impia nam Pietas poſſet ſic veſtra videri.</q>
                  <p>For may it pleaſe your Maieſty to conſider, that in France there are a great number of falſe hearted French men, vnto whom the peruſing of this booke is as dangerous as the fome of a mad dogge, when it falleth on any part of a mans body, being already either diſeaſed or vlcerated.</p>
                  <p>But he which hath written it <hi>(Madam)</hi> is a <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall:</hi> and if the conſideration thereof take place in your generous heart, it will befall you as it did ſometimes vnto King <hi>Demetrius,</hi> (whom <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> haue ſurnamed the indiſcreet Prince) becauſe after hauing a long time laide a ſiege, yea, ſweated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the towne of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and imployed both his blood and treaſure, to become Maſter thereof; hee neuertheleſſe at laſt did loſe both the honour and
<pb facs="tcp:14117:7"/>fruit of his victory; for the reſpect which he bare vnto a naked picture of <hi>Protogenes,</hi> which he very ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently loued, and deſired to conſerue; and ſo deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted from battering that part of the towne, where that table was: by which quarter of the towne he might eaſily haue ſurpriſed and taken it.</p>
                  <p>In the ſelfe ſame manner (you <hi>Madam</hi>) vnto whoſe children the precedent Kings of France haue (for the ſpace of twelue hundred yeares) with much care and trauell, reduced the Crowne thereof to all Soueraignty, and acknowledging to hold it of none but of God (though otherwiſe moſt religious) haue both daunted and brought to reaſon, the <hi>Bonifaces</hi> and <hi>Iulies</hi> (authors of ambition, and bladders puft vp with the winde of vaine glorie) are now brought to loſe the libertie of the King your ſonne, if you incline and bend your ſelfe to admire the dignity of this <hi>Cardinall;</hi> who is to be eſteemed no other then a vaine picture in reſpect of the matter whereof he treateth: vnleſſe couragiouſly you ſacrifice not to the fire, the rodde wherewith this impudent <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> doth imploy his beſt endeuours, to ſcourge the Soueraignty of France.</p>
                  <p>When queſtion is to aſſault a ſtrange Citie, or a Caſtle eſteemed impregnable, none vndertake to attempt it without great and notable preparatiues: ſo this <hi>Cardinall</hi> hath long ſince both premeditated and propens'd to aſſault the ſoueraignty of the Crowne of France; which cannot be won without good &amp; valable conditions. For it is a Cat that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſurpriſed without gloues: But ſift we more narrowly their proceedings.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:7"/>
                  <p>Firſt at Rome they watered and mollified the Maieſty of his chiefe court of Parliament (eſteemed at all times the <hi>Paladium of France</hi>) in the water of the pretext of Religion; contradicting &amp; cenſuring his <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>reſt,</hi> ſo religiouſly and iuſtly giuen againſt that <hi>Parricide Caſtell;</hi> and ſince perceiuing that France was thereof become inſenſible, and as it were ſicke of a Lethargie, becauſe ſhe had ſwallowed downe this ſweet and ſugred pill of Reſpect and Piety, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the See of Rome, (as the royal Dolphin, king of fiſhes, who hauing eaten the ſweet fiſh <hi>Pompilia,</hi> doth with the ſweetnes thereof become ſo drunke, that all his ſenſes are benummed, and as it were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with a Lethargy; ſo as falling vpon the Sand of the ſhore, he there dieth, and is deuoured of the birds of the ayre) they reſolue to aduance further, and continuing to allure him with the ſuger of the ſame deuotion, they definitiuely determine wholly to exterminate this independant Monarchy, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to make him the prey and benefice of all thoſe Sophiſters and flatterers, whom the Pope pleaſeth to repleniſh and ſurfet.</p>
                  <p>But as the poore Dolphin amidſt his pangs of death, (of all his naturall faculties) hath ſtill his eyes open to behold his miſery: right ſo, <hi>Lethargique France,</hi> at leaſt before thou die, retaine thy ſight that thou mayeſt ſee the miſery wherinto the booke of this <hi>Cardinall</hi> will bring thee.</p>
                  <p>Cardinall, a ſplendant &amp; glorious name: but vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? why only vnto ignorant people, as the deceit of the Fowler daſleth the eyes of Larkes and Linits
<pb facs="tcp:14117:8"/>with the reflex of peeces of a Looking-glaſſe, which they repreſent them, but neuer daſleth the eyes of generous <hi>Lyons,</hi> which are not affrighted at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing ſhadow of a light Enſigne, nor at the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition of a nocturnall Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>And who will not repute thee feeble, and taxe thee of cowardiſe generous France, Lyon of all Crownes (as the Lyon is King of all beaſts) if the reſpect of a Redde Hatte ſhould haue power to ſtoppe the courſe of thy independency? It is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lyon, that with the ſound of his voyce he aſſembleth all beaſts to appeare before him; and therefore thou French Lyon, aſſemble, require, and inuite all the Potentates and Princes of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to ſee the fraudulency of this ſecond <hi>Menecli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> who inſenſibly would throw effeminatnes into the ſpirits of Princes, of purpoſe to make them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, not tributaries, but ſubiects to a Prieſt: to a Prieſt worthy indeed to be beloued, as long as he maintaineth himſelfe Prieſt of the world, and Lord or King of his owne territories, without extending his ſhooe in <hi>Idumea;</hi> and ſtriuing that thoſe which in temporall matters are but ſtrangers to him, ſhould neuertheleſſe in that regard be as homagers and ſubiects vnto him.</p>
                  <q>In Idumeam extendam Calciamentum meum, mihi alieni genae ſubditi ſunt.</q>
                  <p>We reade of the Trozenians, that in <hi>Hercules</hi> Clubbe they heretofore ſaw an Oliue branch mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with repoſe and ſecurity: and France I ſay vnto
<pb facs="tcp:14117:8"/>thee, that out of thy reſiſtance, as of a warlike wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, wil ſpring vp thy conſeruation and peace. And although at firſt it ſeeme ſomewhat ſtrange vnto thee, to ſee a <hi>Cardinals</hi> booke publikely burnt by a common hang-man; I neuertheleſſe aduertiſe thee, that this thy anger will proue vnto thee as the ſweetneſſe of moſt medicinall hearbs, as the taſte of the moſt effectuall Antidots, which are ſharp in the palate, and diſtaſtfull in the mouth; but worketh ſtrongly with nature, and exceedingly nouriſheth and comforteth the whole body.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that renowned <hi>Caeſar</hi> had neuer conſeru'd his dignity, if he had not conſidered what it was to haue paſſed the riuer Rubicon with his Army.</p>
                  <p>And France thou ſhalt neuer vphold thy Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, if thou found the paſſage of the profound Amelyte riuer of negligence; vpon the bankes of which thou haſt a long time ſlept, and as it were thy ſelfe at eaſe, ſtretched to receiue the filth of the firſt which attempteth to blemiſh thy incomparable beauty.</p>
                  <p>And if the Naramones ſeeing the South winde had dried vp all their Ceſternes (in battell array) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to ſeeke out his Origine, thereby to fight and be reuenged of him: O France, France, what ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou to do againſt the peſtiferous winde of this Cardinals booke, which attempteth to drie vp the perpetuall ſource of thy Crowne and Kingdomes Soueraignty?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Steneleides Ephore</hi> of Lacedemonia counſelled the Spartans, to beare to the gates both the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons
<pb facs="tcp:14117:9"/>and wou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds of thoſe which violate their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: but at the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt I am not ſo bloudy, neuertheles did occaſion require, I would not be the laſt for ſo good a ſubiect. But France, I with <hi>Publius</hi> the Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an content my ſelfe to aduertiſe thee, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie firſt receiued and not reuenged, draweth on a ſecond, and that this ſecond will ſoone bring thee a third, if thou winke thereat and diſſemble it vnder the cloake of Religion.</p>
                  <p>Briefly I tell thee, that this <hi>Cardinals</hi> booke is the ſame to thee that <hi>Epeus</hi> horſe was to the Troians, that is to ſay in good French, he will be thy ruine: for in his entrailes he hideth a thouſand ſharpe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, to ſubuert the Maieſty of thy Kings, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to metamorphoſe thy tranquility into a combuſtion. I haue read that <hi>Pythagoras</hi> adored the Altars of <hi>Apollos</hi> Temples in Delos, becauſe they were neuer ſacked nor ruinated: and I beleeue like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that the world will reuerence France, becauſe ſhe was neuer brought vnder the yoake of ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſlauerie.</p>
                  <p>But alas poore France, thou now remembreſt not, that as aunciently for ſacrifices the quieteſt beaſts were ſooneſt done to death and immolated: ſo likewiſe at preſent thy exceſſiue piety to the See of Rome, proueth to be the chiefeſt cauſe of thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
                  <p>Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſhould haue addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the King of Spaine, to haue practiſed theſe pranckes in his Dominions, for he hath ſhewed vs how we ſhould beare ourſelues. For when <hi>Baronius</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14117:9"/>(likewiſe <hi>Cardinall</hi>) wrote a Treatiſe of the Sicilian Monarchy: this King which for Sicilia is the elected and feuditorie heyre of the Popes, ſo well ordered his affaires, that the moſt audacious durſt not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to publiſh what the ſaid <hi>Baronius</hi> had written of that matter. Many countreys ſubiect to his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, yea, and his Officers bore themſelues ſo brauely in the diſcharge, that neither the Pope nor Cardinall hath ſince reaped any benefite thereof; yea and will or nill, they were forced ſo to content themſelues both within Italy, as alſo in Kingdomes which yearely contribute many hundreds to the Church of Rome And yet we in France are afraid of our ſhadowes. If there be replie made, that the king of Spaine hath as iuſt cauſe to except at this Booke, as the king of France; in a word, I anſwer, that the quality of the eſtates of theſe two king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes are very much different, and that Rome hath not rounded France in the eare as ſhe hath done Spaine. The wiſer ſort vnderſtand me, <hi>Et ecce my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterium quod vobis dico.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now, what will the aduerſaries of the Romane Religion ſay, ſeeing that the Sea of Rome, which was heretofore the tree of life, is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an Oleander and a Vgh tree, whoſe conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſhadow killeth thoſe which thinke to repoſe themſelues vnder the ſweeteneſſe of their bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
                  <p>O deceitfull verdure of religion, which like that of the North Sea, doſt couer by the faire greene paſſages of the holy Scriptures wreſted, the ſhelues
<pb facs="tcp:14117:10"/>and rockie places where all the Lordſhips of the world ruine themſelues, and ſuffer ſhipwracke.</p>
                  <p>No, no France, it is no longer time to diſſemble: for as <hi>Pyndarus</hi> violated the peace contracted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Greeks and Troians, through the leueling of one arrow at <hi>Menelaus,</hi> ſo this <hi>Cardinall</hi> through the arrow which he hath ſhot forth againſt the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of France (the which he hath not exempted from the Popes bondage) induceth vs to eſteeme the familiarity of the Sea of Rome, to be full of feare and ſuſpition.</p>
                  <p>I haue heretofore heard the Abbot of <hi>Boys Oliuier</hi> report (being a perſon ſufficiently knowne for the good offices which he daily performeth, both to the Church of Rome, and his King) that this preſent Pope <hi>Paulus Quintus,</hi> is very affectionately addicted to France, and that this <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine</hi> is a man very deuout, and of a moſt innocent life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. But now I begin to ſuſpect and doubt the fidelity of this Abbot; for the booke now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and approued and authoriſed by the Pope, doth apparantly teſtifie the contrary. For doth his Holineſſe loue France? why then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth he that this <hi>Cardinals</hi> booke ſet it on fire? and if the Cardinall himſelfe be a deuout and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent man, why giueth he not to France that which he oweth? I meane by ſeparating and diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it from other kingdomes (which for the moſt part) are feuditory and tributary to Popes.</p>
                  <p>I will yet further tie my ſelfe to the relation of this Abbot (for he is knowne to be a Prelate ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere
<pb facs="tcp:14117:10"/>and faithfull, that he will rather die then ſpeake one thing and thinke another) and will rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that a great part of this fault proceeded tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the negligence of the kings intelligencers at Rome, and namely of <hi>Monſieur de Marquemont,</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor of Rota, which hath yearely great penſions from the king, and neuertheleſſe was not ſo well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed to diſcouer the imprinting of this booke: whereof if he had certified <hi>Monſieur de Breues</hi> (his Maieſties Ambaſſadour) he would ſo powerfully and valably haue conferred with the Pope, that his Holineſſe weighing his allegations and reaſons (at leaſt) if he had loued France, would haue preuented the impreſſion therof; and the Cardinall, were he ſo deuout and innocent, would himſelfe haue abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the publiſhing thereof: eſpecially ſith both the one and the other well knew what trouble this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary booke would occaſion in all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And as for vs (reſpecting our Kings minori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wherein it was publiſhed) we can ſay no other then
<q>Scorpius inſidias illa ſub caute tetendit.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe amongſt vs which eſteeme themſelues cleerer ſighted then others, thinke that the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this booke is a tricke meerely inuented by the ſociety of Ieſuites, purpoſely to replunge France in the miſeries, from whence the late deceaſed King had miraculouſly withdrawen it: eſteeming that ſect to reſemble frogges, which are neuer well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are in the mire. Which if it be ſo, the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites
<pb facs="tcp:14117:11"/>may properly be parallel'd to the trees of the Forreſt Lytania, which inuite trauellers to come and repoſe themſelues vnder the delectable ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of their branches, and then being ſet downe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly fall on them and kill them; for all their ſpeeches are nothing but of peace, of matters of ſtate, and of the dignitie of France, (which indeede draweth many of their ſide and faction) ſo as if in the meane time they ſell vs, we ſhall be cunningly deceiued: but my comfort is, that there is a great difference and diſtance betwixt the ſale and deliuery of vs.</p>
                  <p>I ſay if this come to paſſe, to auoyde their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tepriſes it were better wee ſurpriſed them: for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it will befall vs, as it did the Marriners of the Lake of Laumont (in the Prouince of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couie) in Scotland, which as long as the ſaid Lake was tempeſtuous they paſſe without danger, but being calme they alwayes endure ſhipwracke. And alas, who hath better and fitter meanes to annoy vs then the Ieſuites, who confeſſe the King, impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately ſolicite the Queene, liue as companions with <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Chancellor, and <hi>Monſieur Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leroy?</hi> of whom through their dexterity they may obtaine many things, which may tend to our ruine, as aduice and agents to thoſe which employ them thereunto.</p>
                  <p>I am not ignorant that their ſpeeches and bookes are more ſweeter then the Syrens ſongs, and that many good ſpirits (pricked forwards with the ſpurre of Religion) throw themſelues headlong
<pb facs="tcp:14117:11"/>into the Sea of their acquaintance, morefully to participate of their harmony: But I know likewiſe that as the winde ſprong vp which conducted <hi>Butes</hi> out of danger, and ſaued him in Lybia: ſo the winde which at preſent bloweth againſt them in France, hath drawen many excellent ſpirits forth the Sea of their captiuity, and hath fortunately brought them to the port of happines.</p>
                  <p>For conſidering more narrowly why they are ſo applauded, and with a circumſpectious eye behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the forme of their comportments yea and not onely in their faces, but in their liues and doctrines, yea in their very hearts and actions; they affirme they haue found nothing but death for life, euill for good, the loſſe of the Church for her preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and the loſſe of the eſtate for his confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
                  <p>As for me, if ſuch they are, I am of opinion, that there was neuer ſpell nor charme more ſtronger and powerfull, then that wherewith they practiſe. For when I do ſee a <hi>Sillery</hi> and <hi>Villeroy,</hi> (both ſpirites ſhining with bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and on all ſides enuitoned with piercing ſights, which as two <hi>Argus,</hi> haue rather their heads in their eyes, then their eyes in their heads) to be ſo inchanted and lulled aſleepe with the diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling ſongs of thoſe treacherous <hi>Mercuries;</hi> which perceiue not that in ſhutting their eyes to their practiſes, they both cloſe vp and finiſh the dayes of their own honor, and eclipſe the ſplendor of the dignity of France their deere mother and ſweete
<pb facs="tcp:14117:12"/>Countrey, which hath ſo honourably imparted them the choyce of her chiefeſt dignities, and yet of whom they will rauiſh her chiefeſt Iö (to wit) her independency and ſoueraignty, whereof this great <hi>Iupiter</hi> in <hi>Bellarmines</hi> booke doth demonſtrate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe deſperatly enamoured.</p>
                  <p>I am beſides my ſelfe, and beleeue all and more too, which antiquity hath reported of <hi>Circes</hi> the Magician.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Capitolian Iupiter</hi> durſt neuer haue aſſaulted our French <hi>Hercules</hi> in the face, but when he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his backe turned, then heſent this couragious canker Sophiſter <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> ſweating with the blood of Princes, to wound him in the heele. But couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, couragious, the wound is not yet mortall: for (<hi>(Iolaus)</hi> the inflexible Parliament of Paris will cure him: yea and ſo manage and operate, that this <hi>Ixion</hi> which thought himſelfe cock-ſure, to haue embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced our French <hi>Iuno,</hi> ſhall in ſtead thereof onely em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a cloud, from whence ſhal iſſue <hi>Centaures,</hi> that ſhall go through all countries, bleſſing thoſe which will receiue them, yet neuertheleſſe ſhall not be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained in France, which was neuer ordained to be <hi>Augeas</hi> ſtable.</p>
                  <p>And as <hi>Theron</hi> King of Spaine, knocking at the gate of <hi>Hercules</hi> Temple, was with his whole Fleete miraculouſly conſumed by a clap of lightning from heauen: right ſo this booke beating at the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of France, ſhall iudicially be conſumed to cynders, together with all his Sophiſticall reaſons. This being incident and fatall to France, that as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:14117:12"/>vitious perſon entred into the Temple of <hi>Vulcan</hi> on mount Aetna, but was by the guardians thereof deſtroyed and rent in pieces: ſo there was neuer any ill affected to the Flower-deluces, which heretofore hath publiſhed their impoſtures, but by the vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the Parliaments haue beene both defaced and burnt. And although the late troubles haue ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the doores of France, and ſo let in ſome indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and pernitious bookes: as ſometimes forrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners came and caſt ancre in <hi>Diomedes</hi> Ilands, wherein the habitation was onely permitted to the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, becauſe there were certaine birds which <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes</hi> brought thither, which would not endure that any others ſhould peaceably reſide there, except thoſe which were of <hi>Diomedes</hi> country: ſo as if they found any forrainers or ſtrangers there, thoſe care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full birds would violently fall on them, picking and tearing their faces, yea and biting their armes and breaſts, and neuer forſake them vntill they had ſlaine them. In the ſame manner in this Kingdome are carefull and watchfull Parliaments and Magiſtrates, which our Kings haue eſtabliſhed, that will neuer permit that the enemies of the ſtate ſhould violate their priuiledges, or infringe their authority. And although for a time either through importunity or protection of great perſonages, they winke as if they ſaw nothing, &amp; ſo permit them to inhabite amongſt vs: Neuertheleſſe they will neuer tolerate themlong to dwell peaceably amongſt vs, but vvill cloſely and violently purſue them, vntill they haue both exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated and exterminated them, yea and neuer wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:14117:13"/>themſelues to bite and ſting them continually, but proue as faithfull as the dogges being Porters of <hi>Mineruaes Iliadnes</hi> Temple in Dulia, which by a naturall inſtinct alwayes bit thoſe which came to prophane the Temple: yea although they were brought in by her Prieſt, which vnder colour of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was deceiued by thoſe deteſtable propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
                  <p>It is reported that the Liſards crooked teeth, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing once taken hold, cannot be remoued without breaking them. Let vs therefore breake the crooked teeth of this Liſard <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> to the end he leaue vs in our auncient liberty and freedome.</p>
                  <p>It agreeth well with Rome to haue a Pantheon wherein to adore the generality of Gods; but France can ſerue onely one Maſter. And to ſpeake truely, the cauſes which concerne the Temporalitie of France ought not to be cenſured, much leſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided in the Conſiſtorie of Rome. For were that tolerated, it were the direct way to put in practiſe the couſenage of ſubtle <hi>Ithacus,</hi> who before the Grecian army, would pleade the proceſſe of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and ingenious <hi>Palamedes,</hi> to the end the ſub<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to depoſe &amp; ſtone this innocent Prince, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this while to cloake treaſon with a diſſembling ſhew of iuſtice and equity, reſembling the Popes which oueruaile their vſurpation with the ſcarfe of Religion.</p>
                  <p>But if <hi>Iupiter</hi> inflamed with choler, commanded the Riuer <hi>Acheron</hi> to remoue and deſcend into hell, becauſe the water therof refreſht the <hi>Tytans</hi> his
<pb facs="tcp:14117:13"/>mortall enemies, which rebelled againſt him. So what Iudge is there in France which will not be cheerefull, yea willing to controlle, yea conſound ſuch Stationers Libraries, &amp; running Book ſellers, which cauſe ſeditious and pernitious pamphlets to alight on the hearts of thoſe which are enemies and rebels, to their Prince and countrey, to incourage and harden them in the execution of their wicked plots and proiects?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eneas</hi> (ſurnamed the Pious) threatned with a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell death thoſe Ruteloys, which furniſhed his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my <hi>Turnus</hi> with armor and weapons; and the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyriens burnt the citie of Cillena, becauſe the Hele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians being Lords thereof, had aided the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans their enemies: and ſhall our Iudges winke at the aſſiſtance and aide which theſe Booke-ſellers giue the enemies of France, by diſperſing and ſelling this booke of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> which moſt ſecretly and dangerouſly they ſow and diſtribute?</p>
                  <p>No France, no: if the Ieſuites participate of this wickedneſſe, entertaine them no longer as compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and friendes: for being aduanced and riſen through the fauour which thou haſt beſtowed on them, they vſe thee as the Scythian ſlaues did their Maſters; eſteeming themſelues worthy to aſpire to their nuptiall beddes: ſo the Ieſuites beleeue they may both ſport and doe what they pleaſe with the Soueraignty of France. But once curbe and correct them with the whip, and thou ſhalt ſee they will take heed to offend thee. For I cannot more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly compare them then to the beaſts Teuterydes,
<pb facs="tcp:14117:14"/>which feare and flie at thoſe which aſſault them, and vehemently aſſault and follow thoſe which permit them to repoſe and reſt in peace.</p>
                  <p>Anciently, wiſe <hi>Vliſſes</hi> conceiued an extreme horrour, when his ſeruant <hi>Eumenius</hi> informed him, what theft and ryot the louers of his wife <hi>Penelope</hi> committed and acted in his houſe. But now King, Queene Regent, Princes, Iudges, Magiſtrates, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and commons of France, would we might be ſhowen the dangerous Maximes of this Cardinals booke, &amp; the ſpoyle of ſubuerſion, which it preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to doe in France; if you, I ſay, foreſee not and procure the ſuppreſſion and extirpation therof: yea, be ye all inflamed thereat with iuſt anger; for there is therein included and comprehended ſuch dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous poſitions and bloudy propoſitions, that it is to be feared, they will occaſion the Kings Palaces and Cities to reſemble the Cities and Palaces of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia, wherein was nothing heard but cryes and ſighes, nothing ſeene but lamentations and teares.</p>
                  <p>Iudicious Queene, let not the apparent and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling remonſtrances of a <hi>Nuncio,</hi> deceiue your vigilancy: For herein your Maieſty may pleaſe to remember the Egyptian fable of the Crocodile, who vpon the ſhores of Nylus hauing ſurpriſed a childe from his mother, cryed out as he bore him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, <hi>I will render him thee againe, if thou canſt define what I thinke:</hi> the mother bitterly weeping, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>I define thou wilt not render him me, therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore him me, for I haue defined aright.</hi> The Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dile
<pb facs="tcp:14117:14"/>replied, <hi>If I reſtore him thee, then thou haſt lied, I will therefore keepe him both for thee and me.</hi> So when the cenſure of the Areſt of Parliament was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of, and made knowne to our Bride and Lord the late King; what promiſes did the Popes <hi>Nuncio</hi> make him, that he would cauſe it to be both remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and reuoked? yea what ſugred ſpeeches gaue he to <hi>Monſieur Chancelier</hi> and <hi>Monſieur Villeroy,</hi> who onely hindred, and with-held that the Court of Parliament impoſed and bent not their authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it? and which of all thoſe faire promiſes hath he ſince accompliſhed and performed? No, no, he well knoweth the humour of the French to be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in new wounds, and forgetfull when they are become more aged, and when they ſhould ſeeke for reuenge thereof: he beleeueth <hi>that amongſt vs hee which hath time, hath life:</hi> or to ſay more properly, <hi>He which is reprined is pardoned.</hi> And ſo much will he now likewiſe doe to preuent the burning of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines</hi> booke: but when the ſhame and feare thereof is paſt, you ſhall neuer obtaine the honour of the libertie of France, whereof this booke will depriue you; yea his promiſes will vaniſh away as ſmoake, knowing well that as <hi>Denis</hi> the tyrant had rather permit himſelfe to be pulled and drawne downe from his Throne, then to mount vpon a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and warlike horſe: ſo the Popes (his Maſters) haue determined neuer to abandon their pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they haue of the Soueraignty of France, or to ſee themſelues reduced and brought to an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority purely Apoſtolike and Sacerdotall; except
<pb facs="tcp:14117:15"/>by meere force of the faithfull Officers of Kings, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates and Princes. It is an <hi>Axiome (Madam)</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to all Ambaſſadours, wheron dependeth ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the glory or the intereſt of the Princes their Maſters.</p>
                  <q>Turpe eſt vinci, ſed non ceſsiſſe Decorum.</q>
                  <p>And to arriue to a Cardinalſhip, there is no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recter way, then effectually to occaſion Kings to ſubmit themſelues to the authority of Popes, which falſely apply and attribute to themſelues this verſe of <hi>Dauids</hi> Pſalme:
<q>Ador abunt eum omnes Reges terrae, omnes gentes ſeruient ei.</q> Which neuertheles belongeth not properly to any of them, but on the contrary to Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>And for <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> he well knoweth that he hath not alwaies taught that which in his booke hee now teacheth, concerning the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of Popes ouer Kings. For were not <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fift dead, hee would make him wedde the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Inquiſition, becauſe hee then taught more conformable to the truth then he now doth.</p>
                  <p>But ſeeing this Cardinals booke now in the hangmans hand, ready to be conuerted into aſhes; I would willingly demaund of him the ſenſe of the ſame demaund which <hi>Cyrus</hi> made vnto <hi>Craeſus,</hi> whom he had vanquiſhed and taken in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bellarmine, who hath called thee without reaſonable motiues, to warre againſt the temporall Soueraignty of
<pb facs="tcp:14117:15"/>France?</hi> And I anſwere my ſelfe (if his booke could ſpeake it would anſwere for him) <hi>The aduancement and ſecurity of the Soueraignty of France, the augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of her honour</hi> (but without thought thereof) <hi>and for euer the eclipſing of the renowne of my authour, with the eternall baniſhment of all his Aahaerents from the Territories of the Flower-de-Luce:</hi> of which ſaith the Euangeliſt, <hi>Salomon</hi> in all his maieſty was neuer ſo maieſticall as it is.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Antipater</hi> would haue reduced the Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians to his ſubiection, they ſaid vnto him, Vſe vs as Citizens, worthy of Lacedemonia, and let our truce bee as preiudiciall vnto vs as it pleaſeth thee, ſo f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rre forth as it redound not to our ſhame.</p>
                  <p>So France ſaith at preſent to the Pope: Vſe me as France, which hath temporally made thee what thou art; and on that which is ſpirituall, extend thy authority as farre as thou canſt: but beware, make not this Crowne thy ſlaue, which (in many partes of Italy) hath made thee King. Otherwiſe thou muſt needes beleeue, if thou durſt vndertake it, that (as <hi>Augustus</hi> ſaid to thoſe which diſſwaded him from hating <hi>Caſsius</hi> and <hi>Brutus,</hi> the murtherers of his adopted father <hi>Caeſar</hi>) God which hath eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med our King <hi>Lewes</hi> the twelfth, worthy the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great <hi>Henry</hi> his father, will make him as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a ſucceſſor of his valour, to conſerue the crown which he hath left him, free from all domination, except that of heauen.</p>
                  <p>For France reſembleth pretious ſtones, the leaſt
<pb facs="tcp:14117:16"/>cracke or haire which is in the luſtre of her Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty cauſeth her to be no longer France, and maketh the valuation of her worth to be exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly debaſed and diminiſhed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bellarmines</hi> booke for a time will be but a ſmall pepin (or kernell) but with growth of yeares he will grow to be a very thicke Forreſt, full of trees and branches; and if it be not in time lopped and prun'd, it will finally ouertop and beate downe the fruit of the French trees life, and infect it as the Salamander which lurketh in the hollow of ſome fruit tree; and ſo through his extreme coldeneſſe, doth by little and little cauſe him to wither and die.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Iupiter</hi> gaue the marueilous rodde vnto <hi>Mercury</hi> his Meſſenger, he accompanied it with ſhame to beare it vnto human perſons (immediatly after <hi>Epimetheus</hi> had framed man.) But I thinke that Ieſus Chriſt the true God was no leſſe careful when he gaue authority to Popes, to accompany them with modeſty, in bearing themſelues diſcreetly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men.</p>
                  <p>I know well that as the Egyptians made Virgins to ſit on Lyons, ſo the diuine prouidence of God hath placed Eccleſiaſticall authority aboue tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall: but ſo, as Popes ought alwayes to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that this ſpirituall authority is without iſſue or earthly production, as a Virgin which hath no children: yea and ought no more forget that Kings are Lions. And as it is eaſie for a Lyon at one faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his teeth to cruſh in ſunder the bones of a Virgin, if ſhe affright him: ſo it is eaſie for Princes
<pb facs="tcp:14117:16"/>to bound vp Popes in their limits, if they once pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to anger them in any thing which concerneth their temp oraltie; for therein conſiſteth their force and power. A good Chriſtian both indeede and name, named Prudence, ſaid,
<q>Non eripit mortalia, qui Regna dat caeleſtia.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Would not Popes in theſe daies reſemble <hi>Aae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> rodde, which voide of leaues, moth eaten and drie, did neuertheſſe in one night budde forth and become greene, in ſuch ſort, that the next morning the children of Iſraell perceiued not a branch with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leaues, not a Troncke depriued of humidity, and ſeparated from his ſappe: but contratiwiſe a tree greenly flouriſhing and loden with fruit. This pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time wherein we liue is not litterally the ſeaſon of the Iſraelites; but ſpiritually of the Iewes, which miraculouſly retaine this rodde by miracle, but make no vſe of the vertue thereof: ſince it was put into the Arke of the Couenant, as faith Sjt. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Hebrewes, chap. 9. it was neuer imployed nor vſed, that we reade of in Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>There are no more <hi>Predericks</hi> in the world: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it is long ſince, that <hi>Iuno Nucerene</hi> was extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, the which in the warres of the Cymbrians, in the turning of a hand made her withered rodde flouriſh.</p>
                  <p>And the Popes deceiue themſelues, to thinke that they alone can make the harmony of the Church, wherein there muſt likewiſe be Kings and Princes; as ſaid <hi>Zeno,</hi> hearing the Muſitian <hi>Amebeus</hi> playing
<pb facs="tcp:14117:17"/>on his inſtruments, that the entrailes, ſinewes, and bones of beaſts, yea wood laid by, accordant num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and arrang'd by equall proportion, make a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and compleat harmony.</p>
                  <p>It is reported of Dragons, that they rot by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies eating of their tailes, and yet without eating any other fleſh then their owne, they cannot againe become yong. So who will beleeue that the Popes for feare of rotting will not circumference them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues within the circle of their power, but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come againe young, they deſire to eate the power of the Princes of the world?</p>
                  <p>Alas, muſt it ſo fall out, that I a Romane Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſhould ſee the Popes reproached, and that in permitting the publiſhing of this Cardinals booke, wherein France is vſed as the baſeſt countrey of the world? They haue forgotten that it is that holy <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicoboes</hi> and mountaine of refuge, that ſtone of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, which <hi>Mahomet</hi> in his Alcoran, not knowing notwithſtanding the ſenſe of his word, ſaid to be built by the hand of the Almighty, for the ſure and inexpugnable guard of his Ieruſalem, to wit the Church. Yea, yea, as ſaid <hi>Hanniball</hi> to <hi>Antiochus</hi> (but to another purpoſe) ſpeaking of the forces of Syria towards the Romanes: there are but too many Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in France, capable to reſiſt <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though copious and abundant in allegations; yea there are in France enough to feather him, and more then enough to feare him.</p>
                  <q>Cur ſpolieris erit, non cur metuaris ab hoſte.</q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:17"/>
                  <p>O wiſe <hi>Villeroy</hi> (vnder the branches of whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and greatneſſe, lurke all thoſe of the Romane faction, which would wound our countrey) ſeeſt thou not that the confuſed light of this <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> ſent amidſt the cloud of the variableneſſe of France doth preſage our tempeſt? and that the fire of his breath, falling vpon the poopes of our veſſels, is the prognoſtication of the turbulency of our waters? But I foreſee that in the end, the tempeſtuous ſtorm of theſe waters will beare downe the Arke of their irregular power of Rome, ſo farre, that it will finally fixe and eſtabliſh it vpon the toppes of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Armenia, where it cannot poſſibly any longer annoy the Kings of the earth.</p>
                  <p>He which foundeth this <hi>Tooſin</hi> (or Watch bell) wiſe <hi>Villeroy,</hi> is one which hath long admired thee, which knoweth very much of thy proceedings, and who daily weepeth at the diminution of the honor of our natiue countrey: to the ſecurity and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation whereof, thy too too great inclination to Rome giueth terrible aſſaults and aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
                  <p>But wherof ſhould we feare? the Clergy of France is rich. But now the queſtion is of the dignity of the Crowne of France, which ſome endeuour to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilate and extinguiſh: and therfore who can hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs with <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> neither to put diſtinction of wealth, places nor perſons, againſt the raſh aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> which ſeeke thereof to depriue vs? and who can iuſtly reproue vs, if with the Syracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſans we holily vſe our weapons, conſecrated to the
<pb facs="tcp:14117:18"/>Temple of the Olympian <hi>Iupiter,</hi> eſpecially ſith it concerneth the defence of our liberty.</p>
                  <p>And if as ſaid <hi>Publius Curulius,</hi> it was lawfull to ſell thoſe trees which were moſt deuoutly conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Apollo</hi> in the Ile of Coee, to build ſhippes for the warres: doubt not Holy Father, but that the Church of France, vſe both Fer feathers &amp; her trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to reuenge her ſelfe of the wrongs which <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> in his booke hath offered to the crowne of France: and as the Athenians ſaued themſelues by the pretious ſtones of the monuments of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed: ſo we likewiſe will ſtone this <hi>Bellarmine</hi> to death with the ſtones of great <hi>Henry,</hi> our late Kings tombe; during whoſe life, if he had publiſhed that which he hath ſince written, that inuincible King would perſonally haue gone and fetched him out of Rome, and ſo in expiation of his irremiſſible of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, haue immolated and ſacrificed him vpon the Altar of the Soueraignty of France.</p>
                  <p>O <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> the warre is now denounced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt France and thee: and remember that we will vſe thee as the Argeans did the Spartans: for whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou recant liuing, dead, or otherwiſe, as long as France is France, not ſuch as thou wouldeſt haue it to be, but ſuch as God hath eſtabliſhed it: thy name amongſt the French ſhall be as horrible and deteſtable as that of <hi>Eroſtratus</hi> in Epheſus, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured in one houre to ſacke and raze downe all which rich Aſia had erected and built in two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares.</p>
                  <p>And if thou deſireſt that thy other books (indeed
<pb facs="tcp:14117:18"/>profitable) and thy name (formerly honourable) ſhould remaine and liue with vs, we ſay vnto thee, as the Romanes ſaid to <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> which intreated them for truce: firſt forſake the liberty of France, wheron thou haſt ſet foote and intruded, and then motion vs for peace. Otherwiſe nor thou, nor thine ſhall euer haue repoſe in France, ſith thou haſt watched the time of our mourning to make vs ſlaues, as did thoſe wicked ſlips of warre (deteſted of olde <hi>Iacob</hi>) viz. <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leuy,</hi>) which deſtroyed the Siche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites in their greateſt miſeries and calamities.</p>
                  <p>Curſed <hi>Tarentula,</hi> loe we denounce thee warre, and will no longer vſe thee as a Cardinall, becauſe thou haſt not vſed vs as free French men, the firſt borne of the Church. Doſt thou imagine to lull vs aſleepe, thereby to bring our moſt ſenſible mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers into a Lethargy? But what ſpeake I? thou art a Ieſuite, and therefore canſt not doe otherwiſe:
<q>Simia ſemper Simia, etiam ſi paurpura veſtiatur.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>O felonious Ieſuites, which reſemble the Nubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Marmorike, that groweth about the body of man purpoſely to deſtroy it. <hi>Sarcophanges</hi> of Troade, which will inhabite alone, and deſtroy all others that dwell neare you: Combuſtible <hi>Pyrauſtes</hi> which by the rayes of your bookes, dart forth a thouſand incendies and fires into Kingdomes: enuious <hi>Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Telcbnes</hi> or <hi>Alaſtors,</hi> which to deceiue the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Commons of France, couer your ſelues with the thicke cloude of religion, and exhauſting the water of ſtinking Styx, powre it out on our heads;
<pb facs="tcp:14117:19"/>not onely of purpoſe to ingender a thouſand miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, but alſo to make vs forget the wholſome Antidots and remedies, which great <hi>Henry</hi> hath adminiſtred to our miſeries. But alas, your water reſembleth the water of the fountaine of Tellos, which is ſo thicke that it cannot bee intermixed with wine, no more then can your helliſh and King-killing Doctrine agree with the French.</p>
                  <p>For although you ſeeme faire in your conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and bookes, yet God preſerue our Soueraigne Monarchie from being wraped and inuelloped, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in your poſitions, or in your exteriour appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; as a Hiſtorian ſaid, that the rich wals of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon (that ſeuenth wonder of the world) were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ouerſpread or touched with Iuy. For as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Maſon (of all things) ought not to beautifie his building with that ruinous herbe, becauſe in ſtead of ſtrengthening it, it will deſtroy it. So a politicke Prince ought in no wiſe permit or tollerate the ſect and ſociety of Ieſuites to reſide in his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, what colour of Religion, of ſpirituall fruit, or of ſaluation of ſoules, ſoeuer they propoſe him; becauſe it is to wedde his eſtate to the vtter ruine and manifeſt deſtruction thereof, in reſpect they vndertake too much, and buſie themſelues too much with the affaires of the State.</p>
                  <p>Know we not by experience, that as the moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienteſt pearles, by the long and often touching them with lead, are conuerted into duſt and earth, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:14117:19"/>the ſoules of the moſt reſoluteſt and pureſt ſubiect becommeth either ſilent, perfidious or diſloyall through their long fequenting and familiarity with the Ieſuites? which haue for their traditiue and rule (like vnto <hi>Philip</hi> King of Macedonia, who deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to make peace with the Grecians, required their chiefeſt Orators to eſtrange them from them;) that immediatly as ſoone as they come neare great perſonages, they might by their tongue and art ſo contriue it, that their moſt loyall and faithfulleſt ſeruants ſhould bee withdrawne from them, to the end that futurely without danger according to his deſire, he might the better plot and manage his proiects, without being diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
                  <p>For proofe whereof, how many excellent men hath father <hi>Cotton</hi> cauſed to be remoued from the Court, to the end hee might domineere alone? Great Cardinall <hi>Perron</hi> (the lampe of learning) ſpeake and ſay freely, how often hath this Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-Hauke aſſayed to out-ſoare you; yea to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braue and eclipſe you neere the deceaſed King? Renouned Portingall, how many elbow-thruſts hath this impudent giuen your reputation? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſeparate you from your King, which neuer aduanced you becauſe of the malicious importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and importunate malice of this <hi>Harpy,</hi> which would ingroſſe vp al for himſelfe and his adherents. And thou, O ſweet ſpirit, golden tongue, the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our time <hi>Fenouillet,</hi> how many times haue you beene aſſaulted by this <hi>Iſmaell,</hi> which could
<pb facs="tcp:14117:20"/>not endure that (neere the King) your pure clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ſhould obſcure his Comedian ſtile, whom you being a Biſhop (nay a worthy Biſhop) eſteeme no more then a poore ignorant Prieſt. And thou <hi>Coeffeteau,</hi> ſo neerely inward with this hunter of Benefices, Priories, and Court preferments, hath not the purity of thy pen beene ſo farre ſuſpected and enuyed by him, that he ſought to tye thee to liue by the price of bloud, which is eſtabliſhed to purchaſe a field to bury and interre thoſe pilgrims which concurre to the Church? And as for thee <hi>Valladter,</hi> with thy deſultory method of writing, thou haſt affrighted this Courtier, which hath brought thee to thy laſt extremity. As for the Biſhoppes of France, he hath alwaies beene their plague, yea they know the complants which they haue made of him, ſo farre as in their Synod to ſuſpend him <hi>à Diuinis.</hi> But there was none but the Abbot of Boys which hath repulſed and repelled his aſſaults; yea and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him to hearken to reaſon, and become tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and conformable; ſeconded by the iudicious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the Popes <hi>Nuncio,</hi> which ſoone perceiued that this maſculine and vigorous ſpirit, was not of the minde nor mettall to adore <hi>Cotton, Belſabub,</hi> God of the flies of the Court; which hath alwaies his Altars imbrued and tainted, with the bloud of the Oxen and Bulles of the Church, to wit, of her moſt learned and excellenteſt Preachers. It is not long ſince, that to imprint in the heart of our yong King, he ſhould make vſe of none but the Ieſuites, and reiect and caſt off all others: this iugler reported
<pb facs="tcp:14117:20"/>his Maieſty, that the King of Polonia (being a magnanimious and heroycke Prince) had with his owne hand ouer throwne and ſlaine the great Duke of Muſcouia, becauſe, quoth this tale-teller, the ſaid King had with him foure Ieſuites, which neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoke him: as if the ſhadow of theſe foure leſuites repreſented him the preſence of <hi>Aymons</hi> foure ſons, which heretofore made <hi>Charlemaine</hi> ſo renowned and feared. And yet notwithſtanding this fable, it is apparantly knowne, that this aforeſaid Polonian King (which by the meanes of theſe foure Ieſuites, this lyer hath made ſo victorious) hath beene him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe both vanquiſhed and ſlaine.</p>
                  <p>Briefly as we reade that <hi>Iupiter</hi> with one ſmall chaine, very eaſily drew al the other Gods after him, and himſelfe could bee drawen by none of them: ſo the Ieſuites in their Troublexiue of <hi>Gretzerus,</hi> report and write <hi>(Being a barrell of wine, and a filthy lodge ſtinking of lyes and blaſphemies)</hi> that this <hi>Cotton</hi> is the Kings Maſter; that his Maieſtie heareth no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maſſes then his, and that hee gouerneth the Queene Regent; and yet the learned Prelates of France well know that he himſelfe is a puny, and in effect nothing. For otherwiſe great Cardinall <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> the Kings ſpirituall Maſter, and great <hi>Almoner,</hi> and the prudent and graue Biſhop of Bayone his firſt Almoner, and the reſt of the kings Almoners, (amongſt whom there are perſonages, alwaies rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy not onely to diſpute, but conuict him, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him all the daies of his life their ſcholar) ſhould be highly debaſed and blamed: and his Maieſties
<pb facs="tcp:14117:21"/>Chaplaines appeare not to be much imployed and buſied.</p>
                  <p>But notwithſtanding this, I ſee not that eyther the king or Queene gouerne or rule the Ieſuites, and that for all the multitude of Benefices &amp; fauors beſtowed vpon them, they cannot yet draw them to loue them, much leſſe to liue as good ſubiects, &amp; containe themſelues in peace, without innouating ſome things amongſt vs: but rather I ſee they alone thinke to draw all France to them, and beleeue themſelues able at one blow, yea and with high wreſtling now in the kings minority, to obtaine that, whereof during the life of great <hi>Henry,</hi> they durſt not preſume to haue dream't. For hardly had this great king ſhut his eyes (and God knoweth if by their meanes, becauſe he at Rome purſued the reparation of the iniury done to his Maieſty, in cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the Areſt of his Court of Parliament, and threatned <hi>Cotton,</hi> that vnleſſe he changed maximes, he would diſpatch him:) yea no ſooner, I ſay, had great <hi>Henry</hi> giuen his laſt adiew to this world, but they built a Citadel in the ſuburbes of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Germanes,</hi> (without that eyther the king or Queene knowing at whoſe expence and charge (whereunto ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture contributed, which were leaſt doubted of) with ſtrong and craftie force and policy ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring to violate the authority of the Parliament of Paris, that thereby they might be permitted to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their Colledge in deſpite, &amp; maugre the whole body of the Vniuerſity. As if to ouercome all, they thought it ſufficient to alleadge they were Ieſuites,
<pb facs="tcp:14117:21"/>as the Temple of <hi>Trophonius</hi> built in Mnatinea needed no other ſtay then the thread of a Spiders webbe.</p>
                  <p>Already through their confidents they inioy the principall offices both of the Parliament and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike authority, eſteeming by meanes hereof, during the Kings minority, ſo to ſecure and inuellop them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the ſtate, that through their intelligences it will be lawfull for them to diuert and turne it as they pleaſe. But I will giue them an aduice, which if they are wiſe, may perchance much ſteade them: and this it is; <hi>Vindekint</hi> Duke of Saxony, hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a ſworne enemy to France, in the raigne of King <hi>Charllemaine,</hi> ſeeing the King to be gone in perſon to the wars of Spaine, addreſſes himſelfe to a certaine Prince of Denmarke, and ſolicited him to inuade France, in reſpect the King was abſent, and his kingdome left deſolate for a prey. But the Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Prince better inſtructed in the conduction of the affaires of France, replied, No, no; reiect (Sir) thoſe ſimple opinions, and deceiue not your ſelfe: for the kingdome of France is neuer vnprouided of his guard. It is I confeſſe a prey; but (I aſſure you) a ſubtle dangerous prey, which deſtroyeth and rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thoſe which attempt to ſurpriſe it.</p>
                  <p>In like manner it is true, that our king is a <hi>Minor,</hi> yea I acknowledge it: but it is alſo true that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of France are very quick ſighted, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous reſolute and vigilant in his Maieſties affairs. And amongſt theſe Magiſtrates there are ciuill Lieutenants, which cannot diſſemble any thing
<pb facs="tcp:14117:22"/>indamageth or preiudiceth France: in reſpect wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Ieſuites are not yet arriued where they deſire, nor haue not ſtroken the marke whereat they aime; yea I know a certaine Magiſtrate which heretofore repoſed vpon the vigilancy of the late king, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remouing or ſtirring for any matter which paſt in Paris, that now watcheth day and night to keepe king <hi>Lewes</hi> the thirteenth from danger; whom God preſerue and protect. Yea and I perſwade my ſelfe, conſidering it was a Iaye, which by his cryes hath diſcouered the aſſault which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath giuen France: that it may likewiſe be true, that a Gooſe by his voyce hath heretofore ſaued the Capitoll of Rome, from the ſurpriſing of the French: and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue alſo that the Ieſuites with all their ſnares and nets, ſhall neuer ſurpriſe this Iaye; to whom France ought to contribute and affoord an yearely memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (as at Rome they yet remember the Geeſe which guarded and preſerued the Capitoll:) becauſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough his crie ſo effectually and fitly made, he hath awakened and arouſed France from her ſlumber, wherein through this Cardinals wicked booke, ſhe was on the point to loſe the life of her liberty.</p>
                  <p>Ha ye Ieſuites, what preſage is this for you, that birdes picke and warre at you? Peruſe, I ſay, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth chapter of Geneſis, what was the dreame of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Baker; and thereunto adde this other place of Scripture: <hi>Speake not euill of the King in ſecret, for the birds of the ayre will reueale it, and the newes therof:</hi> and ſo applying all this together, feare the diſcouery and torment thereof.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:22"/>
                  <p>It may be you thinke that as Dragons cannot obtaine to be Dragons, before they haue caten a Snake; ſo likewiſe you cannot become the moſt furious and redoubtable of the world, before you haue ſwallowed downe and deuoured France. But let me certifie you, that this booke of Cardinall <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> hath awakened vs from our Lethargie, and hath brought vs to the knowlege why the Popes <hi>Nuncio</hi> fauored vs ſo much: and not many moneths ſince was ſo afraide, leſt the Preachers would haue ſtirred vp the Pariſians to haue expelled and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you the Citie. For as an Areſt of the Court of Parliament is of ſmall efficacy and power, without Serieants or Purſuyuants to execute him; ſo were <hi>Bellarmines</hi> booke of ſmall or no vertue, were you not in France (vnder colour of religion and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) to put in practiſe the execution thereof. For the maske is taken off, and we are aduertiſed at our Ladies Church in Paris, if any one deceiue vs.</p>
                  <p>No, no France, thinke not that when queſtion was to ſuppreſſe the ſellers and diſtributers of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Baronius</hi> his booke at Naples, written againſt the Sicilian Monarchy, that then the Popes <hi>Nuncio</hi> remayned ſilent or idle with his armes a croſſe: for there are many hundreds now preſent, which then ſaw his goings and commings, yea which ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard his threatnings. But as thoſe which dwell at the foote of the mountaines of Egypt, are deafe by reaſon of the cataracts &amp; ſluces of Nylus; ſo the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of Naples ſeemed to be deafe, and gaue no
<pb facs="tcp:14117:23"/>occaſion of laughter to the Court of Rome, which triumph when they ſee people tremble, and feare at the threatnings of their <hi>Nuncios,</hi> and feede them ſelues with this vaine vanity, that they doe ſo ſtand in awe of them.</p>
                  <p>Ha, ha, Citizens of Paris, ſend your children to the Ieſuites ſchooles to bee trayned vp by them for good French men, (as <hi>Archelaus,</hi> who ſent <hi>Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophons</hi> children to Lacedemonia to learne the Maieſty of <hi>Sparta</hi>) and you ſhall ſee what do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine they will imprint in their hearts and ſpirits. And this is the leſſon which came from Rome, that the youth of France ſhould be taught by them at the opening of their ſchooles. But ruſh, this inſtruction came too ſoone in the morning: for it findeth the Colledge doores not yet open: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is pitty, being ſhe was ſo lately borne (for the auncient Chriſtians knew not the name of thoſe Ieſuites) leſt before the Colledge bee open to couer, ſhe ſhould take ſome Rheume or Catarre, and ſo wee ſhould haue neede to apply ſome vſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and cupping to warrant her from all diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, thereby to preuent that ſhee infect not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>You Sirs (to wit) you Ieſuites, you haue beene principally aſſiſted by women in the managing and conduction of all your actions, as alſo by thoſe which haue finiſhed the production thereof. For without the fauour and aſſiſtance of ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, your affaires had gone ſtill backewards. But now ſince your maske is diſcouered, that by <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmines</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14117:23"/>booke you teach that France is no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger France, to wit, Soueraigne and indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, the very women themſelues will both ouerthrow and vanquiſh you, (as the women of Lacedemonia, who in battell array diſcomfited the Meſſenians, which came to ſacke and raze their Citie) and if there were but the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Verneull, the Counteſſe of Moret, and the holy Beaue your Agent in the world, they haue too much taſted the odoriferous ſmell which the Flower-de-luces yeeldeth, to permit them to wither by your breathings (I ſay not contagious breathes) for the word had almoſt eſcaped my tongue. And you Lord of Varrane, and Ladies of Garenne: who had there beene of your trade if France had beene no Soueraignty? For had it pleaſed the Pope that you ſhould haue beene baniſhed the Court, and that it had not beene performed; the King then without the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of France was diſpoſable to the Popes pleaſure, and conſequently then vnable to doe you good or aſſiſt you. Whereby it manifeſtly appeareth, that it is the Soueraignty of France, which hath aſſiſted you, nay inriched you and placed you at your eaſe and pleaſures. In reſpect where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, you then ought and are bound to maintaine and defend it. I ſay further that the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of Guerchuille, and Maignelet, Ladies of greater reſpect, and farre higher renowne then the former, would before the others, haue incited the very dogs againſt the Ieſuites, as ſoone as they
<pb facs="tcp:14117:24"/>had heard the tenour of this Cardinall <hi>Bellarmines</hi> booke: and the Biſhop of Paris, whom I beleeue to be a loyall French man, will die with griefe, if his approbation of their innocency, haue any way ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced ſo infamous a crime, as to endeuour by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to rauiſh and depriue France of her indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſoueraignty, vnto whom both he and his owe all, both their wealth and honour. And for the Duke of Eſpernon, he hath ſo farre experience in the deſtruction of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, his moſt deare and debonaire maſter, what miſery and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation this opinion and vniuſt poſition hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned, that maketh Popes the Soueraignes of the kings of France; that I durſt beleeue he wel acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, that to be a true French man, he loſeth not the eſſence of a good Catholique. I come now to <hi>Monſieur Preſident Siguier,</hi> which notwithſtanding he hath beene the kings Aduocat and Lieutenant ciuill of Paris: and therefore well knoweth with what ballances Magiſtrates ought to weigh ſuch drugges: yet I moſt aſſuredly know, that of late he hath vowed to a man of good reſpect and fame, that it were profitable, if the Ieſuites bee permitted to liue in France, they ſhould ſweare to obſerue the French Maximes, or elſe that they ſhould be exiled and baniſhed France. But there is another ſcruple, to wit, that the Proteſtants will reioyce to ſee the Ieſuites purſued: which neuertheles doth not aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh me, that we feare to annoy them which by their bookes and actions ſeeke to depriue vs of our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and haue no compaſſion of vs, whileſt the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations
<pb facs="tcp:14117:24"/>which neerely concerne them, with-hold and reſtraine vs: but of two euils let vs alwaies chuſe the leaſt. The Proteſtants laugh to ſee the Ieſuites purſued, and the Ieſuites en deuour to make vs the Popes bond-ſlaues, who at their pleaſures ſhould lift vp and throw downe our Kings, when, and as often as they liſt. Let vs therefore giue the Proteſtants leaue to laugh, and in the meane time let vs defend our ſelues from the Ieſuites: for the one importeth vs more then the other. And as for me, I had rather (becauſe we cannot doe otherwiſe) that the Proteſtants ſhould laugh to ſee Catholikes purſue the Ieſuites, then that the Ieſuites ſhould triumph to haue the meanes and audacity (through one booke, yea and without ſhot of Musket or Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol) to make the Crowne of France ſlaue and bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the Pope.</p>
                  <p>And for you of the Clergy, you haue cauſe to reioyce, in that your penſion is ill beſtowed on the <hi>Neophyte Pelletier</hi> (for ſo <hi>Cotton</hi> ſtileth him) in reſpect thereby you entertaine him, which (to his power) endeuoureth with <hi>Rapſodies,</hi> and vnapt Apologies, to couer the ſhame of theſe Ieſuites, being the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of your countrey: who was borne in Valoine in low Normandy, whereof (as ſome report) <hi>Iudas</hi> which betrayed his Maſter and our Sauiour Chriſt was natiue.</p>
                  <p>But father <hi>Coeffeteau</hi> (of the order of <hi>Iacobins</hi>) the once great Mynion of the Ieſuites, hath reaped pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite thereby: who (as a ſecond <hi>Themistocles,</hi> ſeeing that the loue which the Perſians bore him, and all
<pb facs="tcp:14117:25"/>the royall entertainment which they ſhewed him, was but onely to ſerue themſelues of him, to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of the Athenians and Greekes: the which he at laſt perceiuing, made a ſhew to ſacrifice to their victory, and ſo ſacrificed himſelfe for the good of his countrey, by exceſsiuely drinking of the blood of the Bull.) Right ſo I ſay this valiant <hi>Coeffeteau</hi> deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceiting and conſidering whereunto tended the courteſie, and intimate familiarity of the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, and at laſt perceiuing they meant to make vſe of him, as the chiefe of the faction, againſt the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of France, he very wiſely maketh ſemblance to ſacrifice to the Roman victory, through his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Popes <hi>Nuncio;</hi> hee diſcouered this Cardinals pernitious booke, and the authour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the Commiſsioner <hi>L'Angloys,</hi> wherby he hath made himſelfe both memorable and remarkable, and hath (vndoubtedly) approued himſelfe to be a loyall hearted and true French man, contrary to the nature of the water of the <hi>Cephuſcen</hi> fountaine, which no ſooner is poured into a narrow veſſell, and loſt his running current, but is inſtantly transformed into greene yee, and ſo by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle obdurating is changed into flint ſtones. For the inward friendſhip which ſince the Kings death the ſaid <hi>Coeffeteau</hi> hath borne and vowed the Ieſuites conditionally they ſhould make him a Biſhop, hath not made him inſenſible of his countreyes wound, but the loue thereof hath cauſed him to produce and bring to light the booke and the matter which it contained, as alſo thoſe which had of them, which
<pb facs="tcp:14117:25"/>the politique Magiſtrate hath found out and ſeized; and ſo hath deliuered them vp to the Preſidents of the high Court of Parliament, which wil ſoone per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that this deteſtable pamphlet is like thoſe huge Pageants, erected at Rome againſt the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menien feaſts, which repreſented Chariots of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, that withinſide were onely full of ſtraw and hay; being as combuſtible as the matter of this Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals booke, which by his title vaunteth himſelfe a Giant, but in effect (as will appeare by his refutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) will proue but a collection and heape of ſcreeds and fragments of I know not what prophane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours vnbound and torne.</p>
                  <p>Now if France deſire to know what I am that haue ſounded this <hi>Tocſin,</hi> I anſwere I am <hi>Memnons Statue,</hi> erected not in Thebes of Egypt, but in Paris of France: and as <hi>Memnons</hi> olde Statue at the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Apollo</hi> was no ſooner warmed with his beames, but he gaue ſo marueilous a crie, as made the Citizens to concurre together: ſo at the riſing and apparition of the leaſt fire whatſoeuer, which pretendeth to burne France, I will no ſooner bee therewith warmed and touched, but I will crie out <hi>Alarum</hi> to ſtirre vp all the world to the diſpelling and extenuating thereof. And put the caſe I am therefore perſecuted and tormented, I notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding will neuer ceaſe to ſound and ring out my <hi>Toc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin</hi> as loud as I can, no more then did <hi>Memnons</hi> Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue when it was halfe diſmembred, &amp; rent in pieces by <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus Reader, whatſoeuer thou art, thou ſeeſt
<pb facs="tcp:14117:26"/>what I am: but if thou art a loyall hearted French man (as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> by the meaſure of <hi>Hercules</hi> foote could imagine the greateneſſe of his whole bodie) ſo by this ſmall Treatiſe conceiue thou the greatnes of my loue to France: the which if it be eyther try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or prouoked by the King or Councell (without departing from my obedience, faith and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church of Rome) ſhall produce very ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible effects: not beleeuing neuertheleſſe that which is reported at Rome, that they are eyther Lutherans or Caluiniſts, which giue vnto God that which is Gods, and will not alſo take away ſome things from Kings to giue to Popes, not yet to bow their knees, humbly to reuerence the Ieſuites,
<q>
                        <hi>Reddite que ſunt Caeſaris Caeſari, &amp; quaeſunt Dei Deo.</hi>
                     </q> Otherwiſe we muſt conclude, that all Magiſtrates of the Crowne of Spaine, and of the renowned Common-wealth of Venice, which diminiſh not a-any thing from their ſoueraignty to pleaſe the Pope were <hi>todos Lutheranos</hi> (all Lutherans:) which no man of iudgement will report, much leſſe affirme. And ſo farewell without farewell.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AN</hi> EXTRACT OF THE REGIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERS OF THE Court of Parliament of PARIS: Againſt the book intituled, <hi>Tractatus de Poteſtate ſummi Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis in temporalibus, aduerſus Guiliel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Barclaium, auctore Roberto Sanctae Eccleſiae Romanae Cardinali Bellarmino.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>William Stansby.</hi> 1611,</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:27"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:27"/>
                  <head>AN EXTRACT OF THE REGIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Court of PARLIAMENT.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eene by the Court, the great chamber of the Tournelle and Edict, aſſembled, the booke intituled <hi>Tractatus de Poteſtate ſummi Pontificis in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralib' aduerſus Guilielmum Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claium, auctore Roberto Sanctae Eccleſiae Romane Cardinali Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmino,</hi> imprinted in Rome by <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew Sanet,</hi> the yeare <hi>1610</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:14117:28"/>concluſions of the Kings Atturney Generall, all heard and conſidered.</p>
                  <p>The ſaid Court hath and doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite, and defend all maner of perſons of what quality or condition ſoeuer, vpon paine of <hi>Crime De Laeſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> not to receiue, retaine, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicat, imprint, cauſe to be imprinted or ſolde the aforeſaid booke, contayning a falſe and deteſtable opinion, tending to the ſubuerſion of <hi>Soueraigne powers,</hi> ordained and eſtabliſhed by God; ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp of ſubiects againſt their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, withdrawing of their obedience, prouoking them to ſet violent handes vpon their royall perſons and eſtates, and to trouble the repoſe and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the VVeale publike. Inioyning and commanding alſo all thoſe which haue copies of the aforeſaid booke, or
<pb facs="tcp:14117:28"/>know who poſſeſſeth them, ſpeedily to reueale and declare them to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Judges; that according to the requeſts of the ſaid Atturney Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, perqurſition may be made, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution done vpon the offendors, as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall require.</p>
                  <p>Alſo the ſaid Court hath and doth make the like prohibition, and defence, vpon paine of the aforeſaid penaltie, to all Doctors, Diuines, Schoole-maſters or others, not to confer, diſpute, write, or teach, eyther directly or indirectly in their Schooles, Colledges, or any other places, the aforeſaid propoſition.</p>
                  <p>Ordayned likewiſe by the ſaid Court, that this preſent Areſt ſhall be ſent to the Bayliffes and Shrieffes of this Kingdome, to be read, publiſhed, inre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred, kept and obſerued according
<pb facs="tcp:14117:29"/>to the tenour and forme thereof; inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning alſo the ſubſtitutes of the ſaid Kings Atturney Generall, to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſee the execution therof: and to certifie the Court monthly of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence therein.</p>
                  <p>Giuen in Parliament the ſixe and twentieth of Nouember. <hi>1610.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>SIGNED. DV TILLET.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:29"/>
                  <head>THE EXTRACT OF AN AVTHOVR, which hath written the <hi>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of our time.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Great number of French were Leaguers, vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Religion, vntill the Duke of Feria (the Spaniſh Ambaſſadour) diſcouered and tooke off the King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Maske, when in the aſſembly of the pretended ſtates in Paris, he demanded the Kingdome of Fraunce in propriety and ſucceſsion for a daughter of Spaine; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that which is written in ſacred Scripture, <hi>Let not the Lillies ſpinne.</hi> And then
<pb facs="tcp:14117:30"/>it was that the chiefe Preſident (in danger of his life) pronounced that good and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Areſt the eight and twentieth of Iuly, 1593, whereby vpon paine of death it was defended to mention or ſpeak of tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Crowne to any other vnleſſe to the true heires thereof; declaring all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters tending to the preiudice of the Salique law: and all other fundamentall lawes, appertaining to the crowne of France, to be of no power, value, force or vertue. And exhorting the Duke of Mayene, to imploy his authority of Lieuetenantſhip, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of Religion the Crowne of France might not fall into the poſſeſsion of a ſtranger, contrary to the lawes of the Kingdome in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe extant and prouided.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14117:30"/>
                  <head>THE APPLICATION thereof, made by MEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NONS <hi>Statue.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Great and notable number of Catholiques, vnder colour of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion adhaered with the Ieſuits vntill now Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> taking off the maske and diſcouering the reaſon why the Pope his Maſter, ſo ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſiſted for the reeſtabliſhment of the Ieſuites in France, when thinking they had aſſuredly opened their Colledge in Paris, he vnder colour to anſwere a certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Hercles,</hi> ſent the forme of that which the ſaid Ieſuites ſhould teach our youth concerning the Soueraignty of the Crowne of France, which hee brought in ſubiection to the Popes pleaſure; againſt that which is written of the Lilleyes <hi>Quae non laborant,</hi> they are no villaines, hired ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants nor ſlaues. And then it was when (with danger of his life) the ſtarue of <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14117:31"/>ſounded, and rung out this ſhrill ſounding <hi>Tocſin,</hi> being the ſeuenteenth of Nouember, 1610. Which vpon paine to be declared Felons and Traytors, diſſwaded al loyal hearted French men, neither to ſpeak nor teach any way, or for any cauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, that Popes can temporally diſpoſe of the Soueraigntie of France: declaring all bookes tending to the preiudice of the French fundamentall Maximes, to be wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and Diabolicall, and exhorting the Biſhops of Paris, <hi>N.N.N.</hi> of Guerchville, Maignelet, the Marchioneſſe of Verneul, Counteſse of Moret <hi>N.</hi> &amp; others to whom it appertaineth, to imploy the honor which they enioy to be borne in France; as alſo their goods, to the end that vnder colour of Religion, the Soueraignty of France (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the laws of God and the kingdom) fall not into the hands of Prieſts: and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly admoniſhing the Sieurs <hi>N.N.</hi> no more to affright and daunt the Magiſtrates w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> watch for the good of the French Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie: nor by artificiall impietie to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the authoritie which they haue neere
<pb facs="tcp:14117:31"/>the perſon of the Queene Regent, to the great preiudice of the Princes of bloud, Lords, loyal Officers, and faithful ſubiects of the Crowne: which as much as in them lieth they diſgrace and caſt downe, to the end they may domineere and gouerne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone after their owne humours. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if after this admonition they neglect to take heede, the Statue of <hi>Memnon</hi> ſhall reueale many packets of ſecrets: and they ſhall ſee that <hi>Mordocheus</hi> although poorely apparelled in Canuaſse, ſhal preſerue both King and State, yea and diſcouer and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale the treacherous complors of thoſe two <hi>Tereſh</hi> and <hi>Bigthon:</hi> For France is now wearie, and reſolued no longer to endure their iugling trickes, and ſleights of <hi>Legier Du. Main.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
